<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-26T23:26:45+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fun Card Games</title><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><entry><title type="html">Pyramid Solitaire: Ready Your Reflexes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pyramid_solitaire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pyramid Solitaire: Ready Your Reflexes" /><published>2022-12-26T19:15:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-26T19:15:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pyramid_solitaire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pyramid_solitaire/"><![CDATA[<p>This simple solitaire from Italy can be played against the clock or with multiple players vying for the fastest win.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/pyramid.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="the-deck">The Deck</h2>
<p>Pyramid Solitaire is played with a 40-card deck (A-7,J-K). You can remove the 8s,9s and 10s from a traditional 52-card deck, or use an Italian deck, which typically contains 40 cards with the same distribution.</p>

<h2 id="the-setup">The Setup</h2>
<p>To begin a round of pyramid solitaire, create a pyramid of five rows of face-down cards, each new row overlapping the previous row by about half a card. Then add the final row of six cards face-up (see above picture). Each row has one more card than the previous, resulting in a pyramid.</p>

<p>Place the remaining cards to the side of the pyramid. These are the drawpile, which you can cycle through in one direction as many times as necessary.</p>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Match pairs with a sum of ten.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The object of pyramid solitaire is to disassemble the entire pyramid card by card, flipping over cards only when <strong>both</strong> the cards beneath it have been removed and it is completely uncovered.</p>

<p>To remove a card, match it with another card that yields a sum of ten. Kings can be removed without pairing, given they are worth ten.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To make the game easier (though perhaps less aesthetic), leave the 8s,9s and 10s in the deck and remove all three face cards.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="points-per-card">Points Per Card</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Card</th>
      <th>Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen</td>
      <td>9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack</td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td>7</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A</td>
      <td>1</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="winning">Winning</h3>
<p>Use you smartphone’s stopwatch function to measure how long you need from start to finish. But watch out– you won’t always win! Forgetting to flip cards and missing matches not only makes you slower but also increases the chance you won’t be able to reach the tip of the pyramid.</p>

<p>A very good time is about 55 seconds, while a good average is somewhere around 90 seconds.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="solitaire" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This simple solitaire from Italy can be played against the clock or with multiple players vying for the fastest win.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Skat: The Three-Player Classic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/skat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Skat: The Three-Player Classic" /><published>2022-12-26T10:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-26T10:34:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/skat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/skat/"><![CDATA[<p>The three-player trick-taker that’s Unesco World Cultural Heritage.</p>

<h2 id="under-construction">Under Construction</h2>
<ul>
  <li>See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skat_(card_game)">Wikipedia article on Skat</a> (with rules)
<img src="/assets/images/skatbuben.jpg" alt="" /></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="threeplayer" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The three-player trick-taker that's Unesco World Cultural Heritage]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Strohmann-Tarock: Nichts für ‘Dummys’!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/de/strawman_tarot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Strohmann-Tarock: Nichts für ‘Dummys’!" /><published>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/de/strawman_tarot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/de/strawman_tarot/"><![CDATA[<p>Ein Zweispieler-Tarock mit offenen Dummykarten auf dem Tisch (Strohmandeln).</p>

<h2 id="die-karten">Die Karten</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Tarock wird mit 54 großformatigen Tarockkarten gespielt. Es gibt vier Farben (Pik, Herz, Kreuz, Karo) sowie die zusätzliche Trumpffarbe “Tarock”, die alle anderen Farben sticht. Fun fact: Die Herkunft des Wortes “Trumpf” leitet sich von der frühen Bezeichnung der Tarocken auf Italienisch, “le trionfi”. Vom Tarock aus fand das Konzept Trumpf seinen Weg in andere Kartenspiele.</p>

<h3 id="die-farben">Die Farben</h3>
<p>Im Gegensatz zu einem französischen Blatt oder deutschen Blatt gibt es beim Tarock <strong>vier</strong> Bildkarten: König, Dame, Kavall (Reiter), Bube.
In weiterem Unterschied zu anderen Karten, nimmt der König den höchsten Platz auf der Stechskala der Farbkarten ein.</p>

<p>Des Weiteren gibt es Unterschiede zwischen den roten und schwarzen Farben: Nach den Bildkarten Kö-D-Ka-B besteht die Stichrangfolge bei den schwarzen Karten aus 10-9-8-7. Bei den roten Karten is nach den Bildkarten das As die höchste Karte der Farbe (A-2-3-4). Es gibt also insgesamt acht Karten pro Farbe.</p>

<h3 id="tarockkarten">Tarockkarten</h3>
<p>Der Stichwert der Tarockkarten entspricht ihrer Zahl, die zwischen 1-21 liegen kann. Die höchste Tarockkarte ist jedoch der “Sküs” (leitet sich vom französischen “excusez” ab– was man vielleicht sagt, wenn man allen Gegnern die Karten sticht :P ). Der Sküs hat keine Nummer, ist aber sozusagen die 22 Tarock, da er alle anderen Karten des Spieles sticht. Sküs, Tarock 21 (“Mond”), und Tarock 1 (“Pagat”) bilden zusammen die “Trull” und sind jeder fünf Punkte wert in der Abrechnung.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="spielbeginn">Spielbeginn</h2>
<p>Als Erstes werden fünfzehn Karten in drei fünfer Packen an jeden Spieler verteilt. Das sind die Handkarten bzw. das Blatt.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Die verbliebenen 24 Karten werden in drei vierer Packenauf verdeckt vor jeden Spieler auf den Tisch gelegt. Diese Karten werden im Laufe des Spiels peu à peu aufgedeckt und können, sobald aufgedeckt, wie Handkarten ausgespielt werden.</li>
  <li>Diese drei vierer Packen werden als Strohmänner bezeichnet.</li>
</ul>

<p>Falls ein Spieler in seinen Handkarten keine Tarocken bekommt, wird neu ausgeteilt.</p>

<p>Nach dem Austeilen prüft jeder Spieler seine Hand und die Vorhand (der Nicht-Geber) sagt, ob das Spiel “aufnehmen” möchte. Möchte er dies nicht wagen, kann der Geber das Spiel aufnehmen.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Wenn beide passen wird trotzdem gespielt, aber um ein “einfaches Spiel”. Das einfache Spiel bringt weniger Risiko und weniger Punkte.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="punkte">Punkte</h3>
<p>Die Punkte beim Strohmann-Tarock sind “wie Geld” und können auf Papier oder mit Pokerchips getrackt werden. “Wie Geld” soll heißen, jeder Gewinn ist eine Auszahlung durch den Gegner. Aufgenommene Spiele bringen mehr Risiko und mehr Gewinn. Auszahlungen bringen auch bestimmte Prämien, die weiter unten aufgeführt sind.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Gewinnart</th>
      <th>Auszahlung</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Claim and Win</td>
      <td>30</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beat Claimer</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Win Unclaimed Game</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="prämien">Prämien</h3>
<p>am Ende des Spiels kann jeder Spieler, Spielaufnehmer oder Gegner, Prämien gewinnen. Im Strohman-Tarock werden Prämien nicht angesagt.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Prämie</th>
      <th>Beschreibung</th>
      <th>Auszahlung</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Gewinne den Pagat (1) im letzten Stich</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trull</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle drei Trulls (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Vier Könige</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle vier Könige</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 40-49 Punkte</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 50 Punkten oder mehr</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="beispielsabrechnungen">Beispielsabrechnungen</h3>
<p>Der Spielaufnehmer gewinnt ohne Prämien. Der Gegner schafft einen Pagat Ultimo trotz Verlust.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Der Gegner schuldet 30 für das Verlieren des Spiels.</li>
  <li>Der Spielaufnehmer schuldet 10 für das Pagat Ultimo.</li>
</ul>

<p>Niemand nimmt das Spiel auf und die Vorhand gewinnt mit 50 Punkten (grandpoint), sowie allen Trullstücken.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Der Geber schuldet 20 fürs Verlieren,</li>
  <li>weitere 20 für den grandpoint</li>
  <li>sowie 10 oberdrauf für die Trull</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Nutze Poker-Chips, um Punkte fassbar zu machen.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="spielablauf">Spielablauf</h2>
<p>Nachdem feststeht, ob jemand das Spiel aufnimmt und jeder seine Karten geprüft und sortiert hat, dreht jeder die erste Karten von links in jedem seiner Strohmänner offen auf.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Falls die Karte Tarock oder König ist, nimmt er diese Karten in seine Hand auf, nachdem der Gegner die Karte gesehen hat.</li>
  <li>Falls die Karte eine Farbkarte niedriger als der König ist, bleibt die Karte offen auf dem Tisch und es dürfen in diesem Strohmann vorerst keine weiteren Karten aufgedeckt werden. Es wird dann mit dem zweiten und dritten Strohmann genauso verfahren.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/dummytarot.jpg" alt="" /><br />
Nachdem in jedem Strohmann mindestens eine Karte aufgedeckt wurde, fängt man an.</p>

<p>Aufdeckte Strohmann-Karten können alternativ zu den Handkarten ganz normal ausgespielt werden. Man kann sich aussuchen, von wo man eine Karte spielt.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Es macht Sinn, die Strohmänner schnell zu verspielen.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nach jedem Stich, in dem eine Strohmannkarte gespielt wurde, wird die nächste Karte aus dem Strohmann aufdeckt nach dem selben Schema wie vorhin: Könige und Tarocke werden in die Hand aufgenommen, Andere Farbkarten stoppen den Prozess und bleiben liegen.</p>

<p>Wenn ein Spieler nach allen Stichen 35 Punkte und zwei Leerkarten (nach traditioneller Abrechnung) oder 36 Punkte (nach vereinfachter Abrechnung) erreicht, hat er gewonnen.</p>

<p>Die Stich- und Punktewerte der Karten sind ganz unten tabellarisch abgebildet.</p>

<h3 id="stiche-gewinnen">Stiche gewinnen</h3>
<p>Der Spielaufnehmer spielt aus. Die Karte mit dem höchsten Stichwert dreht den Stich und der Gewinner des Stichs spielt erneut aus.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Ausspielen ist gut, denn man kann hiermit die Farbe bestimmen und versuchen, den Gegner seiner Tarocken zu berauben damit er später keine mehr hat.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="farbzwang-und-tarockzwang"><strong>Farbzwang und Tarockzwang</strong></h4>
<p>Es gilt Farbzwang, d.h. man ist verpflichtet, die Farbe der ersten ausgespielten Karte zu bedienen.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Wenn man Farbe nicht bedienen kann, muss man Tarock spielen (Tarockzwang)</li>
  <li>Nur wenn man weder die ausgespielte Farbe noch Tarock hat darf man eine Nebenfarbe abwerfen.</li>
</ul>

<p>Die höchste Karte nach Stichwert (nicht nach Punktewert) gewinnt den Stich. Der Gewinner des Stichs spielt aus.</p>

<h3 id="abrechnung">Abrechnung</h3>
<p>Man gewinnt mit 35 Punkten und zwei weiteren Karten bzw. mit 36 Punkten.</p>

<h4 id="punkte-zählen"><strong>Punkte zählen</strong></h4>
<p>Im Tarock wird üblicherweise eine ungewöhnliche Methode verwendet, um Punkte zu zählen: Karten werden in “Dreierlagen” gezählt, heißt, eine Karte wird zu zwei anderen dazugelegt. Von jedem Dreierpack wird die Summe genommen und davon zwei Punkte abgezogen. Es wird einfacher, wenn man zu jeder wertigen Karte zwei Leerkarten legt (einser Karten).</p>

<p>Beispiel:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Herz-Dame / Herz-5 / Tarock 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Pik-Bube / Tarock 14 / Tarock 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>Karo-König / Tarock 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Wenn du es lieber einfach magst, nutze die vereinfachte Punkteskala unten. Es gibt dann 71 Punkte im Spiel. 36 braucht man aber trotzdem zum Gewinnen.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Karte nach Stichwert</th>
      <th>Punkte (traditionell)</th>
      <th>Punkte (vereinfacht)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Andere Tarocken (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>König</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Dame</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Kavall (Reiter)</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Bube</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="spielende">Spielende</h2>
<p>Wenn ein Gegner bankrott ist, ist das Spiel vorbei.</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/StrawmanTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF (EN)</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="zweispieler" /><category term="tarock" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ein Zweispieler-Tarock mit offenen Dummykarten auf dem Tisch (Strohmandeln).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Straw Man Tarot: Not for ‘Dummies’!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/strawman_tarot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Straw Man Tarot: Not for ‘Dummies’!" /><published>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/strawman_tarot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/strawman_tarot/"><![CDATA[<p>A two-player version of Tarot with open dummy cards on the table (Strohmanntarock).</p>

<h2 id="the-cards">The Cards</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This game is played with a 54-card tarot deck. There are four suits (spades, clubs, hearts and diamonds), plus the additional fifth suit “tarot”, which is a permanent trump suit. Fun fact: the origin of the word “trump” comes from the earlier designation of the tarots in Italian, “le trionfi”.</p>

<h3 id="regular-suits">Regular Suits</h3>
<p>In contrast to a regular deck, there are <strong>four</strong> face cards: King, Queen, Knight and Jack.
In further contrast to a regular deck, the kings are the highest cards by trick rank besides the tarots.</p>

<p>There is a difference between red and black suits, too: in hearts and diamonds, the trick rank after K-Q-Kn-J is A-2-3-4, and those are all the cards present in those suits.</p>

<p>In clubs and spades, the trick rank after the face cards is 10-9-8-7, and these again are the entirety of the cards in those suits.</p>

<h3 id="tarot-cards">Tarot Cards</h3>
<p>The trick rank of the tarot cards is equal to their numbers, which go from 1-21. The highest trick rank among the tarots, however, is the “Sküs” (say “skyooz”, derived from French “excusez”– which you might say when taking all your opponents cards :P ). The Sküs does not have a number, but instead looks kind of like the joker of a regular deck. The Sküs, the 21 tarot, called the Mond, and the 1 tarot, called the Pagat, are the three tarots worth the most points and are known as the “honneurs”.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>At the start of the game, fifteen cards are dealt face down in three packs of five to each player. These are your hand.</p>
<ul>
  <li>The remaining 24 cards are distributed face-down in front of each player, alternating dealing three packs of four. These cards are revealed little-by-little as the game proceeds and can be played just like cards from your hand once they’re flipped. This table hand is known as the straw man.</li>
</ul>

<p>If a player has no tarots in their hand after dealing (before flipping the straw man cards), she can request the game be redealt by the same player.</p>

<p>After dealing, each player orders and checks their hand, and the player who didn’t deal decides whether she wants to claim the game, i.e. go for the win.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If both players pass, the game is still played, but it called a simple game (vs. a claimed game).</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="points">Points</h3>
<p>Points in Straw Man Tarot are credits, and can be tracked on paper or with cents or poker chips. The game is played until the opponent runs out of credits, and a short round can be started with 100 credits each. Claimed games give you more credits for winning. If you win, you get paid, if you lose, you pay.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Win Type</th>
      <th>Opponent Pays You</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Claim and Win</td>
      <td>30</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beat Claimer</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Win Unclaimed Game</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="bonuses">Bonuses</h3>
<p>Bonus points in Straw Man Tarot are awarded regardless of whether the player claimed the game, and are not announced beforehand.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Opponent Pays You</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) on the last trick</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Honneur</td>
      <td>Win all three honneurs (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40-49 points</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 points or more</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="example-scoring">Example Scoring</h3>
<p>Player one claims the game and wins without any bonuses. Player two manages a Pagat Ultimo despite losing.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player two owes player one 30 credits for the game,</li>
  <li>and player one owes player two 10 credits for the Pagat Ultimo.</li>
</ul>

<p>No one claims the game, player two wins with 50 points (grandpoint) and collects all the honneurs.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player one owes player two 20 credits for the win,</li>
  <li>another 20 for winning with 50 (grandpoint),</li>
  <li>and 10 more for the honneurs.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="flipping-the-straw-man-cards">Flipping the Straw Man Cards</h2>
<p>After deciding whether to claim the game, after inspecting and ordering your hands, each player flips the leftmost card of each straw man in front of them (the three four-card packs).</p>
<ul>
  <li>If the card is a tarot or king, she takes this card into her hand after showing it to the opponent.</li>
  <li>If the card is a suited card (Heart/Diamond/Spade/Club) lower than a king, the card remains in the straw man on the table face-up and she can’t flip any more cards in this straw man. The player then proceeds to the next straw man and repeats the process.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/dummytarot.jpg" alt="" /><br />
Once at least one card has been revealed in every straw man, and the above process ended, the game begins.</p>

<p>Face-up cards in the straw men can be played as if they were in the hand; the player can choose to play from hand or straw man (just be careful not to use up your whole hand, having only visible cards would be very easy to play against).</p>

<p>After each trick in which a card from the straw man is played, the next card of that straw man is flipped, and again, if it’s a tarot or king, it’s taken into the player’s hand after showing it.</p>

<p>If a player makes at least 35 points plus two cards (see point counting section below), she has won the round. If neither player reaches this amount, the game is a draw.</p>

<p>Trick points are counted based on the scale and method described below.</p>

<h4 id="following-suit-taking-the-trick"><strong>Following Suit, Taking the Trick</strong></h4>
<p>You always are required to play the same suit as the first card if possible.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If you can’t play the same suit, you are required to play a tarot card.</li>
  <li>Only if you can’t play a card of the same suit or a tarot may you discard a card of the wrong suit.</li>
</ul>

<p>The highest card of the same suit (or the highest tarot) takes the trick, and the winner of the trick plays the next card.</p>

<h4 id="trick-points"><strong>Trick Points</strong></h4>
<p>Tarock traditionally uses an unusual method of counting trick points. Group cards into packs of three, add the point values of each card, and then subtract two from the sum. It’s actually fairly easy to count this way, simply group two one-pointer cards like normal tarots or the numbered suits with one higher card, and you can just ignore the one-pointers. Sometimes you’ll end up with multiple high cards in a pack of three.</p>

<p>To win the game, you need at least 35 points and two remainder one-pointers. One-pointers are known as skartindels.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Queen of Hearts / 5 of Hearts / Tarot 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Jack of Spades / Tarot 14 / Tarot 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>King of Diamonds / Tarot 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: If you’re not a stickler for tradition you can use a simplified point system where you just add up the cards’ values normally. No need for counting in threes and subtracting two. This way you need 36 points to win the game.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Card by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Points (Traditional)</th>
      <th>Points (Simplified)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Other Tarots (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knight</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="end-of-the-game">End of the Game</h2>
<p>The game is over when you’ve run your opponent out of chips!</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/StrawmanTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="tarot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A two-player version of Tarot with open dummy cards on the table (Strohmanntarock).]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Offenbacher Tapp: Tarock zu dritt</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/de/tapp_tarock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Offenbacher Tapp: Tarock zu dritt" /><published>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/de/tapp_tarock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/de/tapp_tarock/"><![CDATA[<p>Biete um den Gewinn und trumpfe dich zum Sieg in diesem lustigen Dreipersonentarock.</p>

<p>Ob dein Glück in den Karten steht? Offenbacher Tapp ist eine einfach zu erlernende Variante des geselligen Dreipersonenspiels Tapp-Tarock (auch bekannt als Wiener Tappen).</p>

<h2 id="die-karten">Die Karten</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Tarock wird mit 54 großformatigen Tarockkarten gespielt. Es gibt vier Farben (Pik, Herz, Kreuz, Karo) sowie die zusätzliche Trumpffarbe “Tarock”, die alle anderen Farben sticht. Fun fact: Die Herkunft des Wortes “Trumpf” leitet sich von der frühen Bezeichnung der Tarocken auf Italienisch, “le trionfi”. Vom Tarock aus fand das Konzept Trumpf seinen Weg in andere Kartenspiele.</p>

<h3 id="die-farben">Die Farben</h3>
<p>Im Gegensatz zu einem französischen Blatt oder deutschen Blatt gibt es beim Tarock <strong>vier</strong> Bildkarten: König, Dame, Kavall (Reiter), Bube.
In weiterem Unterschied zu anderen Karten, nimmt der König den höchsten Platz auf der Stechskala der Farbkarten ein.</p>

<p>Des Weiteren gibt es Unterschiede zwischen den roten und schwarzen Farben: Nach den Bildkarten Kö-D-Ka-B besteht die Stichrangfolge bei den schwarzen Karten aus 10-9-8-7. Bei den roten Karten is nach den Bildkarten das As die höchste Karte der Farbe (A-2-3-4). Es gibt also insgesamt acht Karten pro Farbe.</p>

<h3 id="tarockkarten">Tarockkarten</h3>
<p>Der Stichwert der Tarockkarten entspricht ihrer Zahl, die zwischen 1-21 liegen kann. Die höchste Tarockkarte ist jedoch der “Sküs” (leitet sich vom französischen “excusez” ab– was man vielleicht sagt, wenn man allen Gegnern die Karten sticht :P ). Der Sküs hat keine Nummer, ist aber sozusagen die 22 Tarock, da er alle anderen Karten des Spieles sticht. Sküs, Tarock 21 (“Mond”), und Tarock 1 (“Pagat”) bilden zusammen die “Trull” und sind jeder fünf Punkte wert in der Abrechnung.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="spielbeginn">Spielbeginn</h2>
<p>Zu Beginn des Spieles werden sechs Karten in zwei dreier Packs verdeckt in die Tischmitte gelegt. Diese Karten heißen zusammen der “Tapp”.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Im Anschluss werden 16 Karten in vier vierer Packs an alle drei Spieler verteilt.</li>
  <li>Das Spielen beginnt damit, dass die Teilnehmer um die Einzelspielerrolle bieten.
    <ul>
      <li>Je nach Gebot kann man die Tapp-Karten verwenden, um das eigene Blatt zu verbessern.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ziel-des-spieles">Ziel des Spieles</h2>
<p>Bei Offenbacher Tapp ist der Ziel des Spiels, die Gegner bankrott zu spielen, indem man als Einzelspieler gewinnt und dafür ausgezahlt wird, oder als Partnerspieler versucht, den angsagten Sieg des Einzelspielers zu versauen.</p>

<p>Spieler bieten um die Einzelspielerrolle, die mit einer höheren Auszahlung dotiert ist bei Gewinn. Angefangen mit dem Spieler rechts vom Geber (es wird gegen den Uhrzeigersinn gespielt), gucken die Spieler ihre Blätter an und entscheiden und, ob sie das Spiel “aufnehmen” und dafür bieten möchten. In die Entscheidung spielt hinein, dass man bei den meisten Geboten das eigene Blatt mit Karten aus dem Tapp verbessern darf.</p>

<p>Im Spiel insgesamt gibt es 70 Punkte zu gewinnen, der Gewinner muss 36 schaffen.</p>

<h3 id="bieten-prämien-kontern">Bieten, Prämien, Kontern</h3>

<h4 id="bietestufen"><strong>Bietestufen</strong></h4>
<p>Es gibt vier mögliche Bietestufen, die nur der Reihe nach (hintereinander) geboten werden dürfen.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bietestufe (aufsteigend)</th>
      <th>Bescheibung</th>
      <th>Auszahlung</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Dreier</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eins von zwei Dreierpacks aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zweier</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eins der drei Zweierpaare aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Einser</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eine Karte aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende muss ohne den Tapp auskommen.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>In allen Bietestufen außer “solo” darf die Höchstbietende Karten aus dem eigenen Blatt mit Karten aus dem Tapp tauschen. Dies geschieht direkt nach dem Bieten.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Die ausgetauschten Karten dürfen keine Könige oder Trulls sein und zählen zu den eigenen Stichen.</li>
  <li>Die liegengelassenen Karten zählen zu den Stichen der Gegner.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="das-bieten"><strong>Das Bieten</strong></h4>
<p>Beim Bieten können Spieler schieben oder bieten, aber sobald geschoben dürfen sie nicht mehr am Bieteverfahren teilnehmen. Das erste Gebot ist immer “Dreier” und es geht aufwärts zu “Zweier”, “Einser” und “Solo”.</p>

<p>Wenn ein Spieler überboten wird, hat sie immer die Option, das höhere Gebot zu “halten” und für sich selbst zu beanspruchen, oder aber wieder zu überbieten.</p>

<h4 id="beispiele-fürs-bieten"><strong>Beispiele fürs Bieten</strong></h4>

<p>Spieler A schiebt. Spieler B bietet, wird überboten von C und hält dann dieses höhere Gebot. Spieler C verzichtet auf ein noch höheres Gebot.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Spieler A: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “dreier”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “zweier”</li>
  <li>Spieler A: (SKIPPED)</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “ich halte (die zwei)”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “schieben”</li>
  <li>ENDE (Spieler B gewinnt die Versteigerung.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Spieler A bietet, Spieler B überbietet, Spieler C schiebt und der Rest schiebt auch.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Spieler A: “Dreier”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “Zweier”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler A: “schieben”</li>
  <li>ENDE (Spieler B gewinnt die Versteigerung.)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="tappkarten-tauschen">Tappkarten Tauschen</h3>
<p>Ist die Bietephase fertig, werden alle Tappkarten aufgedeckt, damit alle sie sehen können (außer beim Solo, hier bleiben sie verdeckt).</p>

<p>Der Spielaufnehmer tauscht die entsprechende Anzahl Karten (darf aber keine Könige oder Trullstücke aus seinem Blatt verlegen, da diese Karten viel wert sind und direkt zu den eigenen Stichen zählen). Die nicht getauschten Tappkarten kommen zu den Stichen der Gegner.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Man darf gerade aufgenommene Karten auch wieder verlegen, vorausgesetzt, die sind keine Könige oder Trulls. Tarock kann nur verlegt werden, wenn man keine anderen Farbkarten hat (die nicht Könige sind).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Die ausgetauschten Karten werden nicht gezeigt und bleiben geheim. Ausgetauschte Tarocken müssen jedoch vorgezeigt werden.</p>

<h4 id="prämien"><strong>Prämien</strong></h4>
<p>Zusätzlich zum Bieten gibt es Prämien, die von jedem Spieler gewonnen werden können und von den anderen Spielern 50/50 ausgezahlt werden.</p>

<p>Nach dem Bieten, nach dem Austauschen der Tappkarten hat jeder Spieler die Möglichkeit, eine oder mehrere Prämien anzusagen. Wenn sie angesagt und gewonnen werden, ist die Auszahlung höher, als wenn sie nicht angesagt (still) gespielt werden:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Prämie</th>
      <th>Beschreibung</th>
      <th>Auszahlung (still)</th>
      <th>Auszahlung (angesagt)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Gewinne den Pagat im letzten Stich</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trull</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle drei Trullstücke (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Vier Könige</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle vier Könige</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 40-49 Punkten</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 50 Punkten oder mehr</td>
      <td>40</td>
      <td>80</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="kontern"><strong>Kontern</strong></h4>
<p>Ist das Bieteverfahren und die Prämienansage abgeschlossen, haben die anderen Spieler die Möglichkeit zu kontern.</p>

<p>Durch das Kontern verdoppelt sich die Auszahlung des Spiels, ob gewonnen oder verloren.</p>

<p>Beispiel: Spieler C bietet und gewinnt, nachdem alle anderen geschoben haben. Das Bieten ist hiermit abgeschlossen, Niemand möchte eine Ansage machen, aber Spieler A möchte Kontern.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Spieler A: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “Dreier”</li>
  <li>(Tapp wird getauscht, keine Prämienansagen)</li>
  <li>Spieler A: “kontra”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “schieben”</li>
  <li>ENDE (Spieler C gewinnt das Bieten mit einem Kontra und spielt auf doppeltes Risiko.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Beispiel: Spieler C bietet und gewinnt, nachdem alle anderen geschoben haben. Spieler C sagt Trull an. Spieler A möchte die Trull Kontern, nicht aber das Spiel.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Spieler A: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “Dreier”</li>
  <li>(Tapp wird getauscht, keine Prämienansagen)</li>
  <li>Spieler A: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “Trull”</li>
  <li>Spieler A: “kontra auf die Trull”</li>
  <li>Spieler B: “schieben”</li>
  <li>Spieler C: “schieben”</li>
  <li>ENDE (Spieler C gewinnt das Bieten mit einem Kontra auf Trull und spielt bzgl. der Trull auf doppeltes Risiko. Das Gewinnen des Dreiers bleibt ohne Kontra.)</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Man kann sich nicht selbst Kontern. Das Risiko des Konterns verteilt sich auf die beiden anderen, nicht nur den ansagenden Spieler. Man darf sich hierzu nicht absprechen.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="stiche-gewinnen">Stiche gewinnen</h3>
<p>Der Spielaufnehmer spielt aus. Die Karte mit dem höchsten Stichwert dreht den Stich und der Gewinner des Stichs spielt erneut aus. Ausspielen ist gut, denn man kann hiermit die Farbe bestimmen und versuchen, den Gegner seiner Tarocken zu berauben damit er später keine mehr hat.</p>

<h4 id="farbzwang-und-tarockzwang"><strong>Farbzwang und Tarockzwang</strong></h4>
<p>Es gilt Farbzwang, d.h. man ist verpflichtet, die Farbe der ersten ausgespielten Karte zu bedienen.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Wenn man Farbe nicht bedienen kann, muss man Tarock spielen (Tarockzwang)</li>
  <li>Nur wenn man weder die ausgespielte Farbe noch Tarock hat darf man eine Nebenfarbe abwerfen.</li>
</ul>

<p>Die höchste Karte nach Stichwert (nicht nach Punktewert) gewinnt den Stich. Der Gewinner des Stichs spielt aus.</p>

<h3 id="abrechnung">Abrechnung</h3>
<p>Man gewinnt mit 36 Punkten.</p>

<h4 id="stiche-zählen"><strong>Stiche zählen</strong></h4>
<p>Im Tarock wird üblicherweise eine ungewöhnliche Methode verwendet, um Punkte zu zählen: Karten werden in “Dreierlagen” gezählt, heißt, eine Karte wird zu zwei anderen dazugelegt. Von jedem Dreierpack wird die Summe genommen und davon zwei Punkte abgezogen. Es wird einfacher, wenn man zu jeder wertigen Karte zwei Leerkarten legt (einser Karten).</p>

<p>Beispiel:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Herz-Dame / Herz-5 / Tarock 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Pik-Bube / Tarock 14 / Tarock 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>Karo-König / Tarock 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Wenn du es lieber einfach magst, nutze die vereinfachte Punkteskala unten. Es gibt dann 71 Punkte im Spiel. 36 braucht man aber trotzdem zum Gewinnen.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Karte nach Stichwert</th>
      <th>Punkte (traditionell)</th>
      <th>Punkte (vereinfacht)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Andere Tarocken (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>König</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Dame</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Kavall (Reiter)</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Bube</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="auszahlungen"><strong>Auszahlungen</strong></h4>
<p>Wenn ein Spielaufnehmer oder Prämienansager wie versprochen gewinnt, zahlen ihn die anderen Spieler 50/50 aus.</p>

<p>Verliert man ein angesagtes Spiel oder eine angesagte Prämie, zahlt man die Gegner 50/50 aus.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tipp: Nutze Poker-Chips, um Punkte fassbar zu machen.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bietestufe (aufsteigend)</th>
      <th>Bescheibung</th>
      <th>Auszahlung</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Dreier</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eins von zwei Dreierpacks aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Zweier</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eins der drei Zweierpaare aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Einser</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende darf eine Karte aus dem Tapp aufnehmen.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Höchstbietende muss ohne den Tapp auskommen.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Prämie</th>
      <th>Beschreibung</th>
      <th>Auszahlung (still)</th>
      <th>Auszahlung (angesagt)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Gewinne den Pagat im letzten Stich</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trull</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle drei Trullstücke (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Vier Könige</td>
      <td>Gewinne alle vier Könige</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 40-49 Punkten</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Gewinne mit 50 Punkten oder mehr</td>
      <td>40</td>
      <td>80</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="spielende">Spielende</h2>
<p>Das Spiel ist zu Ende wenn der erste pleite geht. :)</p>

<p>Der Gesamtgewinner ist derjenige mit den meisten Chips zu diesem Zeitpunkt.</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/TappTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF (EN)</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="dreispieler" /><category term="tarock" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Biete um den Gewinn und trumpfe dich zum Sieg in diesem lustigen Dreipersonentarock.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Offenbach Tapp: Tarot for Three</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tapp_tarock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Offenbach Tapp: Tarot for Three" /><published>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tapp_tarock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tapp_tarock/"><![CDATA[<p>Win the bid, and trump your way to victory with this chip-based Tapp Tarock variant.</p>

<p>Not just for fortune telling! Offenbach Tapp is a fun trick-taking game with the added fascination of the fifth suit, tarot.</p>

<h2 id="the-cards">The Cards</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This game is played with a 54-card tarot deck. There are four suits (spades, clubs, hearts and diamonds), plus the additional fifth suit “tarot”, which is a permanent trump suit. Fun fact: the origin of the word “trump” comes from the earlier designation of the tarots in Italian, “le trionfi”.</p>

<h3 id="regular-suits">Regular Suits</h3>
<p>In contrast to a regular deck, there are <strong>four</strong> face cards: King, Queen, Knight and Jack.
In further contrast to a regular deck, the kings are the highest cards by trick rank besides the tarots.</p>

<p>There is a difference between red and black suits, too: in hearts and diamonds, the trick rank after K-Q-Kn-J is A-2-3-4, and those are all the cards present in those suits.</p>

<p>In clubs and spades, the trick rank after the face cards is 10-9-8-7, and these again are the entirety of the cards in those suits.</p>

<h3 id="tarots">Tarots</h3>
<p>The trick rank of the tarot cards is equal to their numbers, which go from 1-21. The highest trick rank among the tarots, however, is the “Sküs” (say “skyooz”, derived from French “excusez”– which you might say when taking all your opponents cards :P ). The Sküs does not have a number, but instead looks kind of like the joker of a regular deck. The Sküs, the 21 tarot, called the Mond, and the 1 tarot, called the Pagat, are the three tarots worth the most points and known together as the honneurs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>At the start of the game, six cards are dealt face down in two packs of three in the center of the table. These are called the “tapp” (hence the name of the game).</p>
<ul>
  <li>Sixteen cards are then dealt to each player in four packs of four.</li>
  <li>The game begins by players bidding for the chance to earn points by winning the round.
    <ul>
      <li>Depending on the bid, you can use the tapp cards to improve your hand.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The goal of Offenbach Tapp is to make points by beating your two opponents alone or beating your one opponent together.</p>

<p>Bidding determines who gets to be the single opponent. Beginning with the player to the right of the dealer (game is played counter-clockwise), players look at their cards and judge whether they want to attempt to win the game alone by collecting the majority of possible card points. There are 70 points in the deck, so to win, you need 36. In most cases, if you win the bid, you get to improve your hand with cards from the tapp.</p>

<h3 id="bidding-bonuses-and-countering">Bidding, Bonuses and Countering</h3>

<h4 id="bid-levels"><strong>Bid Levels</strong></h4>
<p>There are four bids that can be made, each subsequent level only possible after one player has bid the previous.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bids in Ascending Order</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Three</td>
      <td>Bidwinnner gets to choose either of the two packs of three cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Two</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the three adjacent pairs of cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>One</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Bidwinner has to play without any cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>In all the bids except the “solo”, the winning bidder has the chance to improve their hand by exchanging with cards from the tapp.</p>

<h4 id="bidding-process"><strong>Bidding Process</strong></h4>
<p>In the bidding, players can pass or bid, but once they pass they are excluded from the rest of the bidding. The first bid is always “three”, and goes up the scale to “two”, “one”, and “solo”.</p>

<p>If a player is outbid, they have the right to accept the higher bid as their own by saying “I hold”, but also the option to raise again to the next highest bid.</p>

<h4 id="bidding-examples"><strong>Bidding Examples</strong></h4>

<p>Player 2 bids, is outbid, and then takes the higher bid as his own. Player 3 decides not to outbid again:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “two”</li>
  <li>Player 1: (SKIPPED)</li>
  <li>Player 2: “I hold (the two)”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 2 wins the bid.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Player 1 bids, player 2 outbids, player 3 passes and players 1 and 2 don’t bid further:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “two”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 2 wins the bid.)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="exchanging-cards">Exchanging Cards</h3>
<p>Once the bidding phase is over, in all games except “solo”, the bidwinner can exchange cards from the tapp, and the tapp is flipped over for all to see. The bidwinner exchanges the specified number of cards, and the discarded cards count towards the bidwinner’s trick points, while the untouched tapp cards belong to the opponents’ tricks. Note: you can discard cards you just picked up.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Kings and Sküs, Mond (21) and Pagat (1) may not be discarded, because they are worth five points each, and would immediately land in your tricks, giving you an unfair advantage.</li>
  <li>Tarot can only be discarded if you have no other suited cards to discard.</li>
  <li>Cards are discarded face-down, unless they are tarots.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="bonus"><strong>Bonus</strong></h4>
<p>After the bidding phase and the exchange of tapp cards, bonus can be announced, which can be won by any player and are also paid out by the other players 50/50. Announced bonuses are worth more (and cost more) than unannounced (silent) bonuses.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out (silent)</th>
      <th>Pay Out (announced)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) in the last trick</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trull</td>
      <td>Win all three Trulls (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40-49 points</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 or more points</td>
      <td>40</td>
      <td>80</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="countering"><strong>Countering</strong></h4>
<p>Once a bid is won and any bonuses announced, players have the option to counter, doubling the points to be won or lost for that game or bonus. This is done by saying “contra” or “I counter the three”, for example. Game and bonus announcements can be countered individually.</p>

<p>Player 3 bids, player 1 counters:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “three”</li>
  <li>(Tapp exchanged, no bonus announcements)</li>
  <li>Player 1: “contra”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 3 wins the bid with a counter, playing for double stakes.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Player 3 bids, player 1 passes and later counters:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “three”</li>
  <li>(Tapp exchanged)</li>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “Trull”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “contra on Trull”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 3 wins the bid, player 2 announces a Trull, which is countered by player 1)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="trick-taking">Trick Taking</h3>
<p>The player who won the bid plays the first card.</p>

<h4 id="following-suit-etc"><strong>Following Suit, etc.</strong></h4>
<p>You always are required to play the same suit as the first card if possible.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If you can’t play the same suit, you are required to play a tarot card.</li>
  <li>Only if you can’t play a card of the same suit or a tarot may you discard a card of the wrong suit.
The highest card of the same suit (or the highest tarot) takes the trick, and the winner of the trick plays the next card. You need 36 points to win the game.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="scoring">Scoring</h3>
<p>At the end of each game, trick points are counted to determine who gets paid how much.</p>

<h4 id="trick-points"><strong>Trick Points</strong></h4>
<p>Tarock traditionally uses an unusual method of counting trick points. Group cards into packs of three, add the point values of each card, and then subtract two from the sum. It’s actually fairly easy to count this way, simply group two one-pointer cards like normal tarots or the numbered suits with one higher card, and you can just ignore the one-pointers. Sometimes you’ll end up with multiple high cards in a pack of three.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Queen of Hearts / 5 of Hearts / Tarot 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Jack of Spades / Tarot 14 / Tarot 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>King of Diamonds / Tarot 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: If you’re not a stickler for tradition you can use a simplified point system where you just add up the cards’ values. No need for counting in threes and subtracting two. You still win with 36.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Card by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Points (Traditional)</th>
      <th>Points (Simplified)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Other Tarots (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knight</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="pay-outs"><strong>Pay Outs</strong></h4>
<p>If the bidwinner wins the game or a bonus as announced, the other players pay her for the win according to the below tables, each paying half the pay out. If the announcer loses, they must pay each opponent half the value.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: Use poker chips to make points more tangible!</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bid</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Three</td>
      <td>Bidwinnner gets to choose either of the two packs of three cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Two</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the three adjacent pairs of cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>One</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Bidwinner has to play without any cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out (silent)</th>
      <th>Pay Out (announced)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) in the last trick</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trull</td>
      <td>Win all three Trulls (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40-49 points</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 or more points</td>
      <td>40</td>
      <td>80</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The game is over when the first player goes broke. :)</p>

<p>The winner is the player with the most chips.</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/TappTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="threeplayer" /><category term="tarot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Win the bid, and trump your way to victory with this chip-based Tapp Tarock variant.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Offenbach Molotov: Do Your Worst!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/offenbach_molotov/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Offenbach Molotov: Do Your Worst!" /><published>2022-12-11T10:45:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T10:45:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/offenbach_molotov</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/offenbach_molotov/"><![CDATA[<p>Get rid of high cards wisely and win with the lowest score in this fiesty Jass.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/offenbachJass.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 36 card deck (6-A), shuffle and divide the deck equally between each player, dealing out in groups of three cards.</p>
<ul>
  <li>With three players 4x3 each.</li>
  <li>With four players 3x3 each.</li>
  <li>With five players, remove the 6 of bells/diamonds and then deal 4+3 each.</li>
  <li>With six players, 3x2 each.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to score as low as possible by make as few and as cheap tricks as possible. And avoid being bombed with a molotov!</p>

<h2 id="scoring">Scoring</h2>
<p>When you win a trick, you add the cards’ point value to your score. The player that makes the final trick gets an additional five points.</p>

<h3 id="molotovs">Molotovs!</h3>
<p>If a molotov appears on the table, the winner of the trick gets bombed another 20 or 50 points. A molotov is three or four cards <strong>of the same suit</strong> in sequence.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Molotov</th>
      <th>Points</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Example</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Small</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>Three-in-a-row suited</td>
      <td>7-8-9 suited</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Large</td>
      <td>50</td>
      <td>Four-in-a-row suited</td>
      <td>9-10-J/U-Q/O suited</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Cards by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Point Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Jack/Unter (“Bur”)</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Nine (“Nell”)</td>
      <td>14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ace</td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen/Ober</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack/Unter</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ten</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nine</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Eight</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Seven</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Six</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>-Making the last trick-</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SUM</td>
      <td>157</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="making-tricks">Making Tricks</h2>
<p>You win a trick by playing the highest card (by trick rank). If you win the trick, you start the next trick. As in other games, any trump card beats even the best card of another suit.</p>

<h3 id="determining-trump">Determining Trump</h3>
<p>The game begins without a trump and the first card played that can’t follow suit becomes the trump for the round. It applies retroactively, so if you already had a jack or nine whose suit is now trump, those become the bur/nell.</p>

<h3 id="following-suit">Following Suit</h3>
<p>When an opponent starts the trick and you have a card of that suit, you must follow suit or play a trump. You can play trump even if you have that suit, but you don’t have to if you don’t have that suit (unless the played suit is trump). If you don’t have the suit played, you can play any card. If you have the suit played, but no trump, you must play the suit.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Exception: you don’t have to follow suit with the Bur (trump jack/unter, the game’s highest card). The nell, however, must follow suit.</li>
</ul>

<p>You are not required to make tricks, and can intentionally lose a trick, as long as you follow suit.</p>

<h2 id="scorekeeping">Scorekeeping</h2>
<p>The two players with the lowest round score write one tally, the highest player writes a “sack”.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If playing with four, one player gets neither a tally nor a sack.</li>
  <li>If playing with five, the lowest three write tallies, the highest writes a sack and the middle one writes nothing.</li>
  <li>If playing with six, the lowest three write tallies, the worst two write sacks and the middle player writes nothing.</li>
  <li>To get “out of the sack”, the player has to make another tally, crossing through the 0 with a line:</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/sack_strich.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The round is over when all the cards have been played.</li>
  <li>The game is over when one or more players reach five tallies. If several players reach five tallies simultaneosly, the lowest score of the final round decides the winner.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="other-jass-resources">Other Jass Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jassa.at">jassa.at</a>: well-curated site of Jass rules and games (in German)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jassen.at/">Book: Jassen in Vorarlberg</a>: extensive book on Jass cards, rules and history, including instructions for 33 diferent games plus a glossary of Austrian cards proverbs :D (in German)</li>
</ul>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/MolotovJassCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="manyplayer" /><category term="jass" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get rid of high cards wisely and win with the lowest score in this fiesty Jass.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lake Constance Jass</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lake_constance_jass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lake Constance Jass" /><published>2022-12-10T10:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T10:39:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lake_constance_jass</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lake_constance_jass/"><![CDATA[<p>Win the bid to choose the trump, make tricks, but don’t fall in the sack!</p>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/constancejass.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 36 card deck (6-A), shuffle and deal each player three cards face down twice, so that each player has a row of six face-down cards in front of them. Then deal cards face-up on top of them, again 2x3. These are your table cards.</p>

<p>Deal another 2x3 cards per player for your hand.</p>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to make tricks as fast as possible to either fulfill the bid, or keep the opponent from reaching it. Win five rounds and you are the victor.</p>

<h2 id="bidding">Bidding</h2>
<p>The game starts by each player inspecting their hand and estimating how many points they will be able to make. There are 157 total points in the game, so it can make sense to start bidding around 60. You must bid in increments of five. The non-dealer begins the bidding and the winner of the bid chooses the trump and plays first.</p>
<ul>
  <li>This can be very decisive because the high bidder will attempt to choose the trump in which she has a “Bur” or “Nell” (see scoring below).</li>
  <li>Variant rule: if you don’t want to choose a trump, you can play “Bock”, “Gais” or “Slalom” (without trumps, eights are worth eight points to compensate)
    <ul>
      <li>Bock: aces highest trick rank, eights worth eight</li>
      <li>Gais: sixes highest trick rank, eights worth eight</li>
      <li>Slalom: alternate Bock and Gais every trick</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="scoring">Scoring</h2>
<p>When you win a trick, you add the cards’ point value to your score. The player that makes the final trick gets an additional five points.</p>

<h3 id="normal-trump-game">Normal (Trump Game)</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Cards by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Point Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Unter/Jack (“Bur”)</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Nine (“Nell”)</td>
      <td>14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ace</td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ober/Queen</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unter/Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ten</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nine</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Eight</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Seven</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Six</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>-Making the last trick-</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SUM</td>
      <td>157</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="bock-top-down">Bock (Top-Down)</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Cards by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Point Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Ace</td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ober/Queen</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unter/Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ten</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nine</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Eight</td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Seven</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Six</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>-Making the last trick-</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SUM</td>
      <td>157</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gais-bottom-up">Gais (Bottom-Up)</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Cards by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Point Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Six</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Seven</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Eight</td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nine</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ten</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unter/Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ober/Queen</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ace</td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>-Making the last trick-</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SUM</td>
      <td>157</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="making-tricks">Making Tricks</h2>
<p>In Jass, you win a trick by playing the highest card (by trick rank). If you win the trick, you get to start the next trick. As in other games, any trump card can beat even the best card of another suit.</p>

<p>In Lake Constance Jass, <strong>you can choose to play a card from your hand or from your table cards</strong>. Once the trick is won, turn over any freshly revealed face-down cards.</p>

<h3 id="following-suit">Following Suit</h3>
<p>When an opponent starts the trick and you have a card of that suit, you must follow suit or play a trump. If you don’t have a card of the same suit, you can play any other card (wrong suit <strong>or trump</strong>).</p>
<ul>
  <li>One exception: you don’t have to follow suit with the Bur (trump Unter/Jack, the game’s highest card).</li>
</ul>

<p>You are not required to make a trick, and can intentionally lose a trick, as long as you follow suit.</p>

<h2 id="scorekeeping">Scorekeeping</h2>
<p>If the winner of the bid fulfills their bid, they write one tally. If they miss it, the opponent writes one tally. If either player makes 20 or less points, they are “in the sack”. This means the winner writes a tally as usual, and the big loser writes a “0”, which is equivalent to a negative tally. To get “out of the sack”, the player has to win another round, crossing through the 0 with a line:</p>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/sack_strich.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>When one player has reached enough points that it’s impossible for the opponent to win, she can say “enough!” to end the game. Otherwise, the game ends when all cards have been played.</p>

<h2 id="other-jass-resources">Other Jass Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jassa.at">jassa.at</a>: well-curated site of Jass rules and games (in German)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jassen.at/">Book: Jassen in Vorarlberg</a>: extensive book on Jass cards, rules and history, including instructions for 33 diferent games plus a glossary of Austrian cards proverbs :D (in German)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="jass" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Win the bid to choose the trump, make tricks, but don't fall in the sack!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Garbage: A Two-Player Easy as Taking Out Trash</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/garbage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Garbage: A Two-Player Easy as Taking Out Trash" /><published>2022-10-13T19:39:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T19:39:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/garbage</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/garbage/"><![CDATA[<p>This easy (and fun) two-player is a good mindless accompaniment to conversation.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/garbage.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 52 card deck (plus jokers if you want some added spice), deal each player 10 cards face-down on a grid of 5x2.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Place the remaining cards in the center to serve as the draw pile.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to fill all ten positions on the grid with the appropriate numbers before your opponent can!</p>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>The starting player draws a card. If it’s between A-10, place it on the appropriate position on your grid and look at the face-down card that was holding the place.</p>

<p>That card can also be played if the space for its number is open on your grid. You may play as many cards in a row as you can put in the correct grid position without interruption.</p>

<p>Whenever you reveal a card you cannot put into position, you discard it and your turn ends.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Facecards are “duds” and always must be discarded, ending your turn.</li>
  <li>Jokers are wild, and can be placed in any space.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The first person to fill all ten positions with A-10 wins!</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Be the first to collect the cards A-10 on a 10-card grid.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pigtail: Japanese Party Hit</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pigtail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pigtail: Japanese Party Hit" /><published>2022-10-13T19:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T19:14:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pigtail</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pigtail/"><![CDATA[<p>This Japanese party game is guaranteed to work even if even you’ve had one Sake too many…
It is suitable for any number of players.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/pigtail.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>Spread your deck out in a circle (like a pigtail) in the center of the table. Finito.</p>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to turn over and play cards without matching the suit of the previous card! If the suits match, you take the whole stack. Finish the game with the least number of cards in your hand.</p>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>Every turn, turn over a card from the pigtail and place it in the center. If the suit is different than the card beneath (or it’s the first card) you’re safe! :sunglasses:</p>

<p>But if you followed a suit with the same suit…take the whole stack into your hand! :smiling_imp:</p>

<h3 id="extra-rule">Extra Rule</h3>
<p>If you have cards in your hand, you can alternatively play a card from your hand. This makes it easier to recover from a big loss. :grin:</p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The person with the most cards in their hand when the pigtail ends is the LOSER :thumbsdown:</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@brianingermany.github.io/oldcardgames</email></author><category term="manyplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Turn over cards from the pigtail. Just not the same suit as your opponent!]]></summary></entry></feed>