<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="de"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="de" /><updated>2022-12-22T01:50:44+01:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fun Card Games</title><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Strohmann Tarock: Nichts für Dummies!</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/strawman_tarot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Strohmann Tarock: Nichts für Dummies!" /><published>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-19T19:57:00+01:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/strawman_tarot</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/strawman_tarot/"><![CDATA[<p>A two-player version of Tarot with open dummy cards on the table (Strohmanntarock).</p>

<h2 id="the-cards">The Cards</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This game is played with a 54-card tarot deck. There are four suits (spades, clubs, hearts and diamonds), plus the additional fifth suit “tarot”, which is a permanent trump suit. Fun fact: the origin of the word “trump” comes from the earlier designation of the tarots in Italian, “le trionfi”.</p>

<h3 id="regular-suits">Regular Suits</h3>
<p>In contrast to a regular deck, there are <strong>four</strong> face cards: King, Queen, Knight and Jack.
In further contrast to a regular deck, the kings are the highest cards by trick rank besides the tarots.</p>

<p>There is a difference between red and black suits, too: in hearts and diamonds, the trick rank after K-Q-Kn-J is A-2-3-4, and those are all the cards present in those suits.</p>

<p>In clubs and spades, the trick rank after the face cards is 10-9-8-7, and these again are the entirety of the cards in those suits.</p>

<h3 id="tarot-cards">Tarot Cards</h3>
<p>The trick rank of the tarot cards is equal to their numbers, which go from 1-21. The highest trick rank among the tarots, however, is the “Sküs” (say “skyooz”, derived from French “excusez”– which you might say when taking all your opponents cards :P ). The Sküs does not have a number, but instead looks kind of like the joker of a regular deck. The Sküs, the 21 tarot, called the Mond, and the 1 tarot, called the Pagat, are the three tarots worth the most points and are known as the “honneurs”.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>At the start of the game, fifteen cards are dealt face down in three packs of five to each player. These are your hand.</p>
<ul>
  <li>The remaining 24 cards are distributed face-down in front of each player, alternating dealing three packs of four. These cards are revealed little-by-little as the game proceeds and can be played just like cards from your hand once they’re flipped. This table hand is known as the straw man.</li>
</ul>

<p>If a player has no tarots in their hand after dealing (before flipping the straw man cards), she can request the game be redealt by the same player.</p>

<p>After dealing, each player orders and checks their hand, and the player who didn’t deal decides whether she wants to claim the game, i.e. go for the win.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If both players pass, the game is still played, but it called a simple game (vs. a claimed game).</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="points">Points</h3>
<p>Points in Straw Man Tarot are credits, and can be tracked on paper or with cents or poker chips. The game is played until the opponent runs out of credits, and a short round can be started with 100 credits each. Claimed games give you more credits for winning. If you win, you get paid, if you lose, you pay.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Win Type</th>
      <th>Opponent Pays You</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Claim and Win</td>
      <td>30</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beat Claimer</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Win Unclaimed Game</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="bonuses">Bonuses</h3>
<p>Bonus points in Straw Man Tarot are awarded regardless of whether the player claimed the game, and are not announced beforehand.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Opponent Pays You</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) on the last trick</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Honneur</td>
      <td>Win all three honneurs (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40 points or more</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 points or more</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="example-scoring">Example Scoring</h3>
<p>Player one claims the game and wins without any bonuses. Player two manages a Pagat Ultimo despite losing.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player two owes player one 30 credits for the game,</li>
  <li>and player one owes player two 10 credits for the Pagat Ultimo.</li>
</ul>

<p>No one claims the game, player two wins with 40 points (absolut) and collects all the honneurs.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player one owes player two 20 credits for the win,</li>
  <li>another 10 for winning with 40 (absolut),</li>
  <li>and 10 more for the honneurs.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="flipping-the-straw-man-cards">Flipping the Straw Man Cards</h2>
<p>After inspecting and ordering your hands, each player flips the leftmost card of each of the three four-card dummy packs in front of them.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If the card is a tarot or king, she takes this card into her hand after showing it to the opponent.</li>
  <li>If the card is a suited card (Heart/Diamond/Spade/Club) lower than a king, the card remains in the straw man on the table face-up and she can’t flip any more cards in this straw man. The player then proceeds to the next straw man and repeats the process.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/dummytarot.jpg" alt="" /><br />
Once a card has been revealed in every straw man, and the above process ended, the real game begins.</p>

<p>The non-dealer now chooses whether to claim the game. If she doesn’t claim, the dealer has the option to do so, and either way the non-dealer plays the first card.</p>

<p>Face-up cards in the straw men can be played as if they were in the hand; the player can choose to play from hand or straw man (just be careful not to use up your whole hand, having only visible cards would be very easy to play against).</p>

<p>After each trick in which a card from the straw man is played, the next card of that straw man is flipped, and again, if it’s a tarot or king, it’s taken into the player’s hand after showing it.</p>

<p>If a player makes at least 35 points plus two cards (see point counting section below), she has won the round. If neither player reaches this amount, the game is a draw.</p>

<p>Trick points are counted based on the scale and method described below.</p>

<h4 id="trick-points"><strong>Trick Points</strong></h4>
<p>Tarock traditionally uses an unusual method of counting trick points. Group cards into packs of three, add the point values of each card, and then subtract two from the sum. It’s actually fairly easy to count this way, simply group two one-pointer cards like normal tarots or the numbered suits with one higher card, and you can just ignore the one-pointers. Sometimes you’ll end up with multiple high cards in a pack of three.</p>

<p>To win the game, you need at least 35 points and two remainder one-pointers. One-pointers are known as skartindels.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Queen of Hearts / 5 of Hearts / Tarot 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Jack of Spades / Tarot 14 / Tarot 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>King of Diamonds / Tarot 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: If you’re not a stickler for tradition you can use a simplified point system where you just add up the cards’ values normally. No need for counting in threes and subtracting two. This way you need 36 points to win the game.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Card by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Points (Traditional)</th>
      <th>Points (Simplified)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Other Tarots (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knight</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="end-of-the-game">End of the Game</h2>
<p>The game is over when you’ve run your opponent out of chips!</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/StrawmanTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="tarot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A two-player version of Tarot with open dummy cards on the table (Strohmanntarock).]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Offenbach Tapp: Tarock zu dritt</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/tapp_tarock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Offenbach Tapp: Tarock zu dritt" /><published>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-18T12:39:00+01:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/tapp_tarock</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/tapp_tarock/"><![CDATA[<p>Win the bid, and trump your way to victory with this chip-based Tapp Tarock variant.</p>

<p>Not just for fortune telling! Offenbach Tapp is a fun trick-taking game with the added fascination of the fifth suit, tarot.</p>

<h2 id="the-cards">The Cards</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/images/tarock.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This game is played with a 54-card tarot deck. There are four suits (spades, clubs, hearts and diamonds), plus the additional fifth suit “tarot”, which is a permanent trump suit. Fun fact: the origin of the word “trump” comes from the earlier designation of the tarots in Italian, “le trionfi”.</p>

<h3 id="regular-suits">Regular Suits</h3>
<p>In contrast to a regular deck, there are <strong>four</strong> face cards: King, Queen, Knight and Jack.
In further contrast to a regular deck, the kings are the highest cards by trick rank besides the tarots.</p>

<p>There is a difference between red and black suits, too: in hearts and diamonds, the trick rank after K-Q-Kn-J is A-2-3-4, and those are all the cards present in those suits.</p>

<p>In clubs and spades, the trick rank after the face cards is 10-9-8-7, and these again are the entirety of the cards in those suits.</p>

<h3 id="tarots">Tarots</h3>
<p>The trick rank of the tarot cards is equal to their numbers, which go from 1-21. The highest trick rank among the tarots, however, is the “Sküs” (say “skyooz”, derived from French “excusez”– which you might say when taking all your opponents cards :P ). The Sküs does not have a number, but instead looks kind of like the joker of a regular deck. The Sküs, the 21 tarot, called the Mond, and the 1 tarot, called the Pagat, are the three tarots worth the most points and known together as the honneurs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/honneurs.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>At the start of the game, six cards are dealt face down in two packs of three in the center of the table. These are called the “tapp” (hence the name of the game).</p>
<ul>
  <li>Sixteen cards are then dealt to each player in four packs of four.</li>
  <li>The game begins by players bidding for the chance to earn points by winning the round.
    <ul>
      <li>Depending on the bid, you can use the tapp cards to improve your hand.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The goal of Offenbach Tapp is to make points by beating your two opponents alone or beating your one opponent together.</p>

<p>Bidding determines who gets to be the single opponent. Beginning with the player to the right of the dealer (game is played counter-clockwise), players look at their cards and judge whether they want to attempt to win the game alone by collecting the majority of possible card points. There are 70 points in the deck, so to win, you need 36. In most cases, if you win the bid, you get to improve your hand with cards from the tapp.</p>

<h3 id="bidding-bonuses-and-countering">Bidding, Bonuses and Countering</h3>

<h4 id="bid-levels"><strong>Bid Levels</strong></h4>
<p>There are four bids that can be made, each subsequent level only possible after one player has bid the previous.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bids in Ascending Order</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Three</td>
      <td>Bidwinnner gets to choose either of the two packs of three cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Two</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the three adjacent pairs of cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>One</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Bidwinner has to play without any cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>In all the bids except the “solo”, the winning bidder has the chance to improve their hand by exchanging with cards from the tapp.</p>

<h4 id="bonus"><strong>Bonus</strong></h4>
<p>In addition to the bids, there are bonuses, which can be won by any player and are also paid out by the other players 50/50.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) on the last trick</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Honneur</td>
      <td>Win all three honneurs (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40-49 points</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 points or more</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="bidding-process"><strong>Bidding Process</strong></h4>
<p>In the bidding, players can pass or bid, but once they pass they are excluded from the rest of the bidding. The first bid is always “three”, and goes up the scale to “two”, “one”, and “solo”.</p>

<p>If a player is outbid, they have the right to accept the higher bid as their own by saying “I hold”, but also the option to raise again to the next highest bid.</p>

<h4 id="bidding-examples"><strong>Bidding Examples</strong></h4>

<p>Player 2 bids, is outbid, and then takes the higher bid as his own. Player 3 decides not to outbid again:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “two”</li>
  <li>Player 1: (SKIPPED)</li>
  <li>Player 2: “I hold (the two)”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 2 wins the bid.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Player 1 bids, player 2 outbids, player 3 passes and players 1 and 2 don’t bid further:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “two”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 2 wins the bid.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Same arrangement, but player 1 tries to announce a bonus:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “two”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “I hold”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “one”</li>
  <li>Player 3: (SKIPPED)</li>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 2 wins the bid.)</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="countering-examples"><strong>Countering Examples</strong></h4>
<p>Once a bid is won, players have the option to counter the win, doubling the points to be won or lost in that round. This is done by saying “contra” or “I counter the three”, for example.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Both bids and bonus announcements can be countered.</li>
</ul>

<p>Player 3 bids, player 1 passes and later counters:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “contra”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “pass”</li>
  <li>END (Player 3 wins the bid with a counter, playing for double stakes.)</li>
</ul>

<p>In rare cases, the player may want to double down on the counter, showing she is even more sure of herself and securing even more potential points by saying “recontra”:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Player 1: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “three”</li>
  <li>Player 1: “contra on the three”</li>
  <li>Player 2: “pass”</li>
  <li>Player 3: “recontra”</li>
  <li>END (Player 3 playes for quadruple stakes on the three.)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="exchanging-cards">Exchanging Cards</h3>
<p>Once the bid is won, in all games except “solo”, the bidwinner can exchange cards from the tapp, and the tapp is flipped over for all to see. The bidwinner exchanges the specified number of cards, and the discarded cards count towards the bidwinner’s trick points, while the untouched tapp cards belong to the opponents’ tricks. Note: you may discard cards you just picked up.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Kings and Sküs, Mond (21) and Pagat (1) may not be discarded, because they are worth five points each, and would immediately land in your tricks, giving you an unfair advantage.</li>
  <li>Tarot can only be discarded if you have no other suited cards to discard.</li>
  <li>Cards are discarded face-up.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="trick-taking">Trick Taking</h3>
<p>The player who won the bid plays the first card. The highest ranked card takes the trick, and the winner of the trick plays the next card. You need 36 points to win the game.</p>

<h3 id="scoring">Scoring</h3>
<p>At the end of each game, trick points are counted to determine who gets paid how much.</p>

<h4 id="trick-points"><strong>Trick Points</strong></h4>
<p>Tarock traditionally uses an unusual method of counting trick points. Group cards into packs of three, add the point values of each card, and then subtract two from the sum. It’s actually fairly easy to count this way, simply group two one-pointer cards like normal tarots or the numbered suits with one higher card, and you can just ignore the one-pointers. Sometimes you’ll end up with multiple high cards in a pack of three.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Queen of Hearts / 5 of Hearts / Tarot 3 = (4 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 4</li>
  <li>Jack of Spades / Tarot 14 / Tarot 18 = (2 + 1 + 1) - 2 = 2</li>
  <li>King of Diamonds / Tarot 12 / Sküs = (5 + 1 + 5) - 2 = 9</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tip: If you’re not a stickler for tradition you can use a simplified point system where you just add up the cards’ values. No need for counting in threes and subtracting two. You still win with 36.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Card by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Points (Traditional)</th>
      <th>Points (Simplified)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Sküs</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mond (21)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Other Tarots (2-20)</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat (1)</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Queen</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knight</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10/A</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9/2</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8/3</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7/4</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="pay-outs"><strong>Pay Outs</strong></h4>
<p>If the bidwinner wins the game as promised, the other players pay her for the win according to the below table, each paying half the pay out. If the bidwinner loses, each opponent gets paid half.</p>

<p>Bonuses are also paid 50/50 by the other players.</p>

<p>Tip: Use poker chips!</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bid</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Three</td>
      <td>Bidwinnner gets to choose either of the two packs of three cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Two</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the three adjacent pairs of cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>One</td>
      <td>Bidwinner gets to choose one of the cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>60</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solo</td>
      <td>Bidwinner has to play without any cards from the tapp.</td>
      <td>100</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bonus</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Pay Out</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Pagat Ultimo</td>
      <td>Win the Pagat (1) on the last trick</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Honneur</td>
      <td>Win all three honneurs (Pagat (1), Mond (21), Sküs)</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Four Kings</td>
      <td>Win all four kings</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Absolut</td>
      <td>Win with 40-49 points</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Grandpoint</td>
      <td>Win with 50 points or more</td>
      <td>40</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The game is over when the first player goes broke. :)</p>

<p>The winner is the player with the most chips.</p>

<h2><a href="/assets/pdf/TappTarockCheatSheet.pdf" download="">Cheat Sheet PDF</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="threeplayer" /><category term="tarot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Win the bid, and trump your way to victory with this chip-based Tapp Tarock variant.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Do Your Worst: Offenbach Molotov!</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/offenbach_molotov/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Your Worst: Offenbach Molotov!" /><published>2022-12-11T10:45:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T10:45:00+01:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/offenbach_molotov</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/offenbach_molotov/"><![CDATA[<p>Get rid of high cards wisely and win with the lowest score in this fiesty Jass.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/offenbachJass.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 36 card deck (6-A), shuffle and divide the deck equally between each player, dealing out in groups of three cards.</p>
<ul>
  <li>With three players 4x3 each.</li>
  <li>With four players 3x3 each.</li>
  <li>With five players, remove the 6 of bells/diamonds and then deal 4+3 each.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to score as low as possible by make as few and as cheap tricks as possible. And avoid being bombed with a molotov!</p>

<h2 id="scoring">Scoring</h2>
<p>When you win a trick, you add the cards’ point value to your score. The player that makes the final trick gets an additional five points.</p>

<h3 id="molotovs">Molotovs!</h3>
<p>If a molotov appears on the table, the winner of the trick gets bombed another 20 or 50 points. A molotov is three or four cards <strong>of the same suit</strong> in sequence.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Small molotov = three in a row
    <ul>
      <li>20 points</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Large molotov = four in a row
    <ul>
      <li>50 points</li>
      <li>Only possible with 4+ players</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Examples
    <ul>
      <li>6-7-8</li>
      <li>J-Q-K</li>
      <li>9-10-J-Q</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Cards by Trick Rank</th>
      <th>Point Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Unter/Jack (“Bur”)</td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trump Nine (“Nell”)</td>
      <td>14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ace</td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>King</td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ober/Queen</td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unter/Jack</td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ten</td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Nine</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Eight</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Seven</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Six</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>-Making the last trick-</td>
      <td>5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SUM</td>
      <td>157</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="making-tricks">Making Tricks</h2>
<p>You win a trick by playing the highest card (by trick rank). If you win the trick, you start the next trick. As in other games, any trump card beats even the best card of another suit.</p>

<h3 id="determining-trump">Determining Trump</h3>
<p>The game begins without a trump and the first card played that can’t follow suit becomes the trump for the round. It applies retroactively, so if you already had a jack or nine whose suit is now trump, those become the bur/nell.</p>

<h3 id="following-suit">Following Suit</h3>
<p>When an opponent starts the trick and you have a card of that suit, you must follow suit or play a trump. You can play trump even if you have that suit, but you don’t have to if you don’t have that suit (unless the played suit is trump). If you don’t have the suit played, you can play any card. If you have the suit played, but no trump, you must play the suit.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Exception: you don’t have to follow suit with the Bur (trump Unter/Jack, the game’s highest card). The nell, however, must follow suit.</li>
</ul>

<p>You are not required to make tricks, and can intentionally lose a trick, as long as you follow suit.</p>

<h2 id="scorekeeping">Scorekeeping</h2>
<p>The two players with the lowest round score write one tally, the highest player writes a “sack”.</p>
<ul>
  <li>If playing with four, one player gets neither a tally nor a sack.</li>
  <li>If playing with five, the lowest two write tallies, the highest two write sacks and the middle one writes nothing.</li>
  <li>To get “out of the sack”, the player has to make another tally, crossing through the 0 with a line:</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/sack_strich.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The round is over when all the cards have been played.</li>
  <li>The game is over when one or more players reach five tallies. If several players reach five tallies simultaneosly, the lowest score of the final round decides the winner.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="other-jass-resources">Other Jass Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jassa.at">jassa.at</a>: well-curated site of Jass rules and games (in German)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jassen.at/">Book: Jassen in Vorarlberg</a>: extensive book on Jass cards, rules and history, including instructions for 33 diferent games plus a glossary of Austrian cards proverbs :D (in German)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="threeplayer" /><category term="fourplayer" /><category term="fiveplayer" /><category term="jass" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get rid of high cards wisely and win with the lowest score in this fiesty Jass.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Lake Constance Jass</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/lake_constance_jass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lake Constance Jass" /><published>2022-12-10T10:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T10:39:00+01:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/lake_constance_jass</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/lake_constance_jass/"><![CDATA[<p>Win the bid to choose the trump, make tricks, but don’t fall in the sack!</p>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/constancejass.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 36 card deck (6-A), shuffle and deal each player three cards face down twice, so that each player has a row of six face-down cards in front of them. Then deal cards face-up on top of them, again 2x3. These are your table cards.</p>

<p>Deal another 2x3 cards per player for your hand.</p>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to make tricks as fast as possible to either fulfill the bid, or keep the opponent from reaching it. Win five rounds and you are the victor.</p>

<h2 id="bidding">Bidding</h2>
<p>The game starts by each player inspecting their hand and estimating how many points they will be able to make. There are 157 total points in the game, so it can make sense to start bidding around 60. You must bid in increments of five. The non-dealer begins the bidding and the winner of the bid chooses the trump and plays first.</p>
<ul>
  <li>This can be very decisive because the high bidder will attempt to choose the trump in which she has a “Bur” or “Nell” (see scoring below).</li>
  <li>Variant rule: if you don’t want to choose a trump, you can play “Bock”, “Gais” or “Slalom” (without trumps, eights are worth eight points to compensate)
    <ul>
      <li>Bock: aces highest trick rank, eights worth eight</li>
      <li>Gais: sixes highest trick rank, eights worth eight</li>
      <li>Slalom: alternate Bock and Gais every trick</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="scoring">Scoring</h2>
<p>When you win a trick, you add the cards’ point value to your score. The player that makes the final trick gets an additional five points.</p>

<h3 id="normal-trump-game">Normal (Trump Game)</h3>
<p>| Cards by Trick Rank      | Point Value |
| ———————— | ———– |
| Trump Unter/Jack (“Bur”) | 20          |
| Trump Nine (“Nell”)      | 14          |
| Ace                      | 11          |
| King                     | 4           |
| Ober/Queen               | 3           |
| Unter/Jack               | 2           |
| Ten                      | 10          |
| Nine                     | 0           |
| Eight                    | 0           |
| Seven                    | 0           |
| Six                      | 0           |
| -Making the last trick-  | 5           |
| SUM                      | 157         |</p>

<h3 id="bock-top-down">Bock (Top-Down)</h3>
<p>| Cards by Trick Rank      | Point Value |
| ———————— | ———– |
| Ace                      | 11          |
| King                     | 4           |
| Ober/Queen               | 3           |
| Unter/Jack               | 2           |
| Ten                      | 10          |
| Nine                     | 0           |
| Eight                    | 8           |
| Seven                    | 0           |
| Six                      | 0           |
| -Making the last trick-  | 5           |
| SUM                      | 157         |</p>

<h3 id="gais-bottom-up">Gais (Bottom-Up)</h3>
<p>| Cards by Trick Rank      | Point Value |
| ———————— | ———– |
| Six                      | 0           |
| Seven                    | 0           |
| Eight                    | 8           |
| Nine                     | 0           |
| Ten                      | 10          |
| Unter/Jack               | 2           |
| Ober/Queen               | 3           |
| King                     | 4           |
| Ace                      | 11          |
| -Making the last trick-  | 5           |
| SUM                      | 157         |</p>

<h2 id="making-tricks">Making Tricks</h2>
<p>In Jass, you win a trick by playing the highest card (by trick rank). If you win the trick, you get to start the next trick. As in other games, any trump card can beat even the best card of another suit.</p>

<p>In Lake Constance Jass, <strong>you can choose to play a card from your hand or from your table cards</strong>. Once the trick is won, turn over any freshly revealed face-down cards.</p>

<h3 id="following-suit">Following Suit</h3>
<p>When an opponent starts the trick and you have a card of that suit, you must follow suit or play a trump. If you don’t have a card of the same suit, you can play any other card (wrong suit <strong>or trump</strong>).</p>
<ul>
  <li>One exception: you don’t have to follow suit with the Bur (trump Unter/Jack, the game’s highest card).</li>
</ul>

<p>You are not required to make a trick, and can intentionally lose a trick, as long as you follow suit.</p>

<h2 id="scorekeeping">Scorekeeping</h2>
<p>If the winner of the bid fulfills their bid, they write one tally. If they miss it, the opponent writes one tally. If either player makes 20 or less points, they are “in the sack”. This means the winner writes a tally as usual, and the big loser writes a “0”, which is equivalent to a negative tally. To get “out of the sack”, the player has to win another round, crossing through the 0 with a line:</p>

<p><img src="../../assets/images/sack_strich.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>When one player has reached enough points that it’s impossible for the opponent to win, she can say “enough!” to end the game. Otherwise, the game ends when all cards have been played.</p>

<h2 id="other-jass-resources">Other Jass Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://jassa.at">jassa.at</a>: well-curated site of Jass rules and games (in German)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jassen.at/">Book: Jassen in Vorarlberg</a>: extensive book on Jass cards, rules and history, including instructions for 33 diferent games plus a glossary of Austrian cards proverbs :D (in German)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="jass" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Win the bid to choose the trump, make tricks, but don't fall in the sack!]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Garbage: A Two-Player Easy as Taking Out Trash</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/garbage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Garbage: A Two-Player Easy as Taking Out Trash" /><published>2022-10-13T19:39:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T19:39:00+02:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/garbage</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/garbage/"><![CDATA[<p>This easy (and fun) two-player is a good mindless accompaniment to conversation.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/garbage.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>With a 52 card deck (plus jokers if you want some added spice), deal each player 10 cards face-down on a grid of 5x2.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Place the remaining cards in the center to serve as the draw pile.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to fill all ten positions on the grid with the appropriate numbers before your opponent can!</p>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>The starting player draws a card. If it’s between A-10, place it on the appropriate position on your grid and look at the face-down card that was holding the place.</p>

<p>That card can also be played if the space for its number is open on your grid. You may play as many cards in a row as you can put in the correct grid position without interruption.</p>

<p>Whenever you reveal a card you cannot put into position, you discard it and your turn ends.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Facecards are “duds” and always must be discarded, ending your turn.</li>
  <li>Jokers are wild, and can be placed in any space.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The first person to fill all ten positions with A-10 wins!</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Be the first to collect the cards A-10 on a 10-card grid.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Pigtail: Japanese Party Hit</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/pigtail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pigtail: Japanese Party Hit" /><published>2022-10-13T19:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T19:14:00+02:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/pigtail</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/pigtail/"><![CDATA[<p>This Japanese party game is guaranteed to work even if even you’ve had one Sake too many…
It is suitable for any number of players.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/pigtail.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>Spread your deck out in a circle (like a pigtail) in the center of the table. Finito.</p>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of the game is to turn over and play cards without matching the suit of the previous card! If the suits match, you take the whole stack. Finish the game with the least number of cards in your hand.</p>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>Every turn, turn over a card from the pigtail and place it in the center. If the suit is different than the card beneath (or it’s the first card) you’re safe! :sunglasses:</p>

<p>But if you followed a suit with the same suit…take the whole stack into your hand! :smiling_imp:</p>

<h3 id="extra-rule">Extra Rule</h3>
<p>If you have cards in your hand, you can alternatively play a card from your hand. This makes it easier to recover from a big loss. :grin:</p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The person with the most cards in their hand when the pigtail ends is the LOSER :thumbsdown:</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="manyplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Turn over cards from the pigtail. Just not the same suit as your opponent!]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Durak: Gang Up on Opponents and Don’t be the Dummy</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/durak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Durak: Gang Up on Opponents and Don’t be the Dummy" /><published>2022-10-12T17:39:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-12T17:39:00+02:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/durak</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/durak/"><![CDATA[<p>Gang up on (defenseless? :grin: ) opponents in this souped-up version of War for 4-8 players.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/durak.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Durak can be played with a standard 52-card deck or, for a faster version, with a 36-card (6-A) deck.</p>
<ul>
  <li>This fast-paced party game is popular in former Soviet countries and well-known in parts of central Europe.</li>
  <li>The game is best with 4-8 players. If playing with more than six, use a 52-card deck.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<ul>
  <li>At the start of the game, each player is dealt six cards.</li>
  <li>An additional card is uncovered and placed under the deck perpendicularly. This is the trump for the round.</li>
  <li>The game begins by the first player putting down a card, an attack on the player to their left.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="object-of-the-game">Object of the Game</h2>
<p>The aim of Durak is to shed all your cards as soon as possible. The last (wo-)man standing is the loser, and is called the Durak, or “dummy”!</p>

<h2 id="attacking-and-defending">Attacking and Defending</h2>
<p>If it’s your turn, it means you’re the first attacker, the person to your left is the defender, and the person on the other side of the defender is the second attacker.</p>
<ul>
  <li>The defender is always surrounded by two attackers! :smiling_imp: (until less than three players remain).</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="attacking">Attacking</h3>
<p>To attack, lay down a card in front of the defender. If you have multiples of the same number, you may lay down as many of that same card down as you like. The defender has to produce a higher card of the same suit (or a trump) for each attacking card.</p>

<p>Here’s where it gets interesting: 
Any time after the first attack has hit the table, the other attacker can also attack with any cards of that same number. And as soon as the defender plays a card, that number, too, is now fair game for the attackers to play and double-down the offense!</p>

<h3 id="defending">Defending</h3>
<p>You don’t have to attempt a defense; sometimes its safer to just take the cards your attacked with and continue the game.</p>

<p>If you succeed in fighting off each and every attack card your opponents play, you’ve succeeding in shedding some cards, and it’s now your turn to be the first attacker and shed some more.</p>

<p>If you can’t defend, pick up all the cards on the table, and your turn is skipped. The player to your left continues.</p>

<h4 id="special-defense">Special Defense</h4>
<p>If you’re attacked with a number you have in your own hand, play it to push the attack off to the next player :sweat_smile:.</p>

<h2 id="drawing-cards">Drawing Cards</h2>
<p>After each failed or successful round of attacks, players draw back to six cards in the following order:</p>
<ol>
  <li>First Attacker</li>
  <li>Second Attacker</li>
  <li>Defender</li>
</ol>

<p>This order is important, because the deck will run out at some point, and the fewer cards you have, the less likely you are to become the Durak!</p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The game continues until every player except one has shed all their cards. Give that dude a funny hat and call him a Durak! The Durak starts the next round.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="manyplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Gang up on (defenseless? ;) ) opponents in this souped-up version of War for 4-8 players.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">66: Ein Klassiker für zwei</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/de/sixty-six/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="66: Ein Klassiker für zwei" /><published>2022-10-09T23:34:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-09T23:34:00+02:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/de/sixty-six</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/de/sixty-six/"><![CDATA[<p>Combine luck with strategy to make tricks and reach 66 before your opponent!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/66.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>66 is played with a 24-card deck, using only the nines through aces.</p>
<ul>
  <li>For added fun, you can use a <a href="https://www.piatnik.com/spiele/spielkarten/regionale-karten/blitz-salzburger">German-face deck</a> as pictured above, but an ordinary pack of cards will work just as well.</li>
  <li>The game is played with 2 players.</li>
  <li>A nearly identical Austrian variant played without the nines (Schnapsen), using only 20 cards.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<ul>
  <li>At the start of the game, each player is dealt six cards (five cards if playing without nines).</li>
  <li>An additional card is uncovered an placed under the deck perpendicularly. This is the trump suit.</li>
  <li>The game begins by the first player playing a card.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>The aim of 66 is to make tricks and announcements to accumulate 66 points before your opponent.</p>

<h3 id="making-tricks">Making tricks</h3>
<p>To make a trick, the opponent must play a higher card of the same suit or a trump card.</p>
<ul>
  <li>You are not required to follow suit or make a trick.</li>
  <li>The player who makes the trick plays the next card.</li>
  <li>After each trick, each player draws another card (until the deck runs out).</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="scoring-of-tricks">Scoring of Tricks</h4>
<p>| Card by Trick Rank | Points |
| —————— | —— |
| Ace                | 11     |
| 10                 | 10     |
| King               | 4      |
| Queen/Ober         | 3      |
| Jack/Unter         | 2      |
| 9                  | 0      |</p>

<h3 id="marriages">Marriages</h3>

<p>Marriages consist of a queen and king (Ober and Unter) of the same suit.</p>
<ul>
  <li>You can make only announce a marriage if it’s your turn to begin the trick, and you must play one of those cards after claiming it.<br />
Marriages are worth the following points:</li>
  <li>40 points for a marriage in trump</li>
  <li>20 points for each non-trump marriage</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="closing-the-deck">Closing the deck</h3>
<p>You can pressure your opponent into the corner by closing the deck (on your turn).</p>
<ul>
  <li>As soon as the deck is closed (or runs out), players are <strong>forced to make a trick or follow suit</strong> if possible.
If the deck was closed, the closing player must win (by reaching 66)!</li>
  <li>If she doesn’t, the opponent receives all the points they would have received, but at least two.
Once the deck has been closed, the defending player does not get points for any tricks or announcements she may make from that time until the end of the round.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="stealing-the-trump">Stealing the trump</h3>
<p>If you have the lowest trump card, you can exchange it when it’s your turn for the trump under the deck.</p>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>If you think you have reached 66 points, just say “66” or “enough!” when it’s your turn to end the round. But watch out– if you don’t actually have 66 your opponent will get extra points! You can look at your tricks at any time.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Even if both players actually have 66, the first one to call it wins.
    <h3 id="scoring">Scoring</h3>
  </li>
  <li>If you make 66 and the opponent has 33 or more, you receive one point.</li>
  <li>If the opponent has less than 33, you receive two points.</li>
  <li>If the opponent has made no tricks, you receive three points.</li>
  <li>If you say “enough!” but don’t have 66, your opponent gets at least two points, or however many you would have won if you had had 66.</li>
  <li><strong>Seven match points wins!</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Loser buys the next round :)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Fun tip with German cards:</p>
<ul>
  <li>You can use one of the sevens covered up by another card to track your match points.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/score66.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="twoplayer" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Combine luck with strategy to make tricks and reach 66 before your opponent!]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="de"><title type="html">Schnauz: Wie Blackjack aber besser</title><link href="/https://funcardgames.net/blitz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Schnauz: Wie Blackjack aber besser" /><published>2022-10-09T14:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-09T14:10:00+02:00</updated><id>/https://funcardgames.net/blitz</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://funcardgames.net/blitz/"><![CDATA[<p>Win by not losing! In this fun Blackjack predecessor, keep your lives to stay afloat.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blitz.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Blitz is played with a 32-card deck, using only the sevens through aces.</p>
<ul>
  <li>For added fun, you can use a <a href="https://www.piatnik.com/spiele/spielkarten/regionale-karten/doppeldeutsche-blitz-36-blatt">German-face deck</a> as pictured above, but an ordinary pack of cards will work just as well.</li>
  <li>The game is played best with 3-7 players.</li>
  <li>It’s also known as 31 or Scat</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<ul>
  <li>At the start of the game, each player is given three lives (matchsticks, coins, etc.).</li>
  <li>Each player is dealt three cards.
    <ul>
      <li>The dealer inspects her cards, and has the option to keep them or put them in the center and take three new cards.
        <ul>
          <li>If the dealer keeps her cards, three additional cards from the deck are placed in the center.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The player to the left of the dealer is first to play.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>The aim of Blitz is to gather three cards of the same suit for the highest score.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Aces are worth 11, face cards 10, and all other cards are worth their number value.</li>
  <li>Each turn, players may exchange <em>one or all cards, but not two</em>.</li>
  <li>The round ends in one of three ways:
    <ol>
      <li>A player reaches 31 points</li>
      <li>A player has three aces (blitz).</li>
      <li>A player closes the round
        <ul>
          <li>Closing is denoted by knocking and is only possible after the first round.</li>
          <li>If you choose to close, you may not exchange cards, and the game ends after every other player has one more chance to play.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="end-of-game">End of Game</h2>
<p>The player(s) with the lowest score loses one life. Once all a player’s lives are gone, she is “swimming” on one final life, after which she loses.</p>

<h2 id="additional-important-rules">Additional Important Rules</h2>
<ul>
  <li>If a player gets three aces, the game is immediately over, and every other player loses one life.
    <ul>
      <li>“Blitz!”</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Three-of-a-kind is worth exactly 30.5 points.</li>
  <li>You can always pass instead of exchanging cards or closing.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="strategy-tips">Strategy Tips</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The earlier you can get a high score, the earlier you can “knock” to jump the gun on opponents that haven’t had time to collect points.</li>
  <li>Make sure you don’t accidentally create a good hand in the bank by exchanging cards.
    <ul>
      <li>Remember, the next player can take all three cards!</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Brian Junker-Latocha</name><email>brian@funcardgames.net</email></author><category term="manyplayer" /><category term="easy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Win by not losing! In this fun Blackjack predecessor, keep your lives to stay afloat.]]></summary></entry></feed>